Guide to the Ella Fountain Pratt Papers, circa 1850-2008
Duke University. University Archives
Ella Fountain Pratt papers circa 1850-2008
Duke University. University Archives
Pratt, Ella Fountain
18 linear feet Extent: 13,000 Items
Ella Fountain Keesler Pratt (1914-2008) was a Duke University employee for almost thirty years. Ms. Pratt was also a patron of the arts and community organizer in Durham, North Carolina. This collection contains documents, records, photographs, and notes that document her life as a Duke employee and Durham arts organizer. Items include personal notebooks, photographs of family and events, art exhibition catalogs, and audio recordings of performances at Duke University. The collection materials range in date from circa 1850 to 2008.
RL.01574
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Ella Fountain Pratt Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2009 and 2012.
Biographical Note
Ella Fountain Keesler Pratt was born in Greenwood, Mississippi in 1914. After graduating from high school, she attended Mississippi State College for Women (now known as Mississippi University for Women) from 1932-1936, where she frequently took part in theatre, dancing, and art-related activities. After graduation, Ella studied dance in New York City and taught classes in Mississippi and at Sullins College in Bristol, Virginia. Ella married her sweetheart, Lanier W. Pratt, in 1938 and the couple moved to Durham, North Carolina in 1940 where Mr. Pratt was a graduate student at Duke University. Lanier taught in the Classics department after graduation, eventually rising to the rank of Professor and then Dean. Illness caused Mr. Pratt's untimely death in 1956. That same year, Duke University hired Ella Fountain to help develop an arts program for the recently formed Student Union.
From 1956 to 1984, Ella Fountain helped shaped the arts community at Duke University by expanding the Student Union's art collection, helping organize exhibitions and artist talks, as well as enticing world famous performers like Itzhak Perlman, Leontyne Price, and Jean-Pierre Rampal to perform as part of the Duke Artists Series. Upon her retirement from the University, hundreds of letters of love and support flooded in from Duke students, alumni, faculty members, and administrators. But Ella's work with the arts was not done.
Over time, Ms. Pratt became a vital member of the Durham arts scene, contributing her ideas and experience to the Durham Arts Council. During her tenure as a DAC executive, she managed a grant program for Emerging Artists, helped paved the way for the American Dance Festival's relocation to Durham, and made possible a host of memorable performances including many concerts a folk festival featuring Pete Seeger, and several performances by the Triangle Opera. In 2002, a grand gala was given to celebrate her life's work with the arts and her accomplishments as a member of the Duke and Durham communities.
Ella Fountain Pratt died in 2008 at the age of 94.
Collection Overview
The Ella Fountain Pratt Papers contain materials pertaining to Pratts's personal life and professional accomplishments. A majority of the collection is comprised of personal correspondence, records, and news clippings that document Ella's education, her participation in the Durham Arts scene, and her experiences as a longtime employee at Duke University. Newer accessions also include photographs (largely unidentified and undated) of both Ella and her husband as well as their sons and Mr. Pratt's family as well as genealogical information, Mr. Pratt's correspondence, and materials pertaining to his education and work at Duke University, in addition to his service in the U. S. Navy during World War II. Of note is a letter signed by Richard Nixon soon after he was defeated in the 1960 election. The collection also includes notable autographs of the various artists Ella Fountain Pratt encountered during her lifetime. Items in the collection range from circa 1850-2008, with the bulk from 1960-2000.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is in roughly chronological/biographical order when possible, though much of the material is undated.
Nitrate negatives contained within the collection are in cold storage offsite. Due to conservation concerns, the negatives are non-circulating. Many of these images have been scanned and are available on the DVDs stored onsite at the University Archives.
Subject Headings
Pratt, Ella Fountain; Arts -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University, Durham, N.C.; Duke University. Museum of Art -- Exhibitions; Durham Council for the Arts; Durham (N.C.)
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (18 boxes)
  - Pre-College School Papers, 1920-1975 (Box 1)
  - MSCW, 1932-1936 (6 folders)
  - Diploma from MSCW, 1936
  - Sullins College Programs, 1936-38
  - Scrapbook Materials, 1930-1936 (2 Folders)
  - Lanier Pratt Scrapbook, circa 1940-1956 (2 Folders)
  - Travel Papers and Documents, circa 1955-1995
  - Personal Papers, Notes, Programs and Ephemera, circa 1965-2004 (5 Folders)
  - Duke Student Union Records, 1956-1980 (2 Folders)
  - Duke Student Union Records, 1956-1980 (2 Folders) (Box 2)
  - Duke Artists Series, circa 1970-1990 (2 Folders)
  - Duke Artists Series Programs, 1972-2005 (5 Folders)
  - Student Union Art Collection, 1964-1968 (2 Folders)
  - Duke Acquisitions Procedures, 1965-1966
  - Mailing Lists for Exhibitions and Catalogs, 1963-1969 (2 Folders)
  - Visual Arts Committee Correspondence, 1968-1969
  - Visual Arts Committee Insurance, 1967-1970 (2 Folders)
  - North Carolina Arts Council Records, 1978-1979
  - NEA Internship Info, 1972-1978
  - Program and Notes for Bernstein's "Mass", 1978
  - Art Exhibitions Brochures, Flyers, and Catalogs, circa 1963-1980 (4 Folders)
  - Art Exhibitions Brochures, Flyers, and Catalogs, circa 1963-1980 (3 Folders) (Box 3)
  - Lecture Programs and Bulletins, 1952-1982
  - Town and Campus Club Celebrates 65 Years, circa 1981
  - Friday Morning Music Study Club, undated
  - Durham Arts Council, circa 1967-2008 (4 Folders)
  - Triangle Opera Programs and Papers, 1986-2000 (4 Folders)
  - Miscellaneous Arts Programs and Papers, circa 1980-1997
  - Robert Ward Celebration Documentation, 1987 (2 Folders)
  - Durham Cultural Master Plan, 2002
  - Miscellaneous Professional Papers and Programs, circa 1967-2001 (Box 4)
  - Fanfare and Events Honoring Ella Fountain Pratt, circa 1984-2000
  - Fanfare Notes for Ella, 2000 (2 Envelopes)
  - Journals and Personal Notebooks, circa 1940's-2006 (11 Envelopes, 2 Folders)
  - Correspondence, circa 1930-2008 (15 Folders) (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1928-2008 (5 Envelopes)
  - Clippings, 1928-2008 (23 Envelopes (Box 6)
  - Black and White Photographs, circa 1930-2000 (9 Folders) (Box 7)
  - Black and White Promo Photographs, 1970-1990 (6 Folders)
  - Color Photographs, circa 1960-2008 (2 Folders)
  - Color Photographs, circa 1960-2008 (2 Folders (Box 8)
  - Durham Arts Council's Photographs, circa 1980-1990
  - Durham Friday Morning Music Study Club Photos, circa 1985-2000
  - Photo Negatives, circa 1930-2008
  - DVDs of Scanned Images, circa 1930-2008
  - Slides, circa 1960-1975
  - Thad Sparks at Duke University Slides, 1975
  - "Mass" Performance Slides, 1978
  - Harper Jr. High Slides, 1977
  - The Duke Endowment [book]
  - Hero by the Hour [play/book]
  - Seventeen [book]
  - Little Women [play/book]
  - Meh Lady, 1933 [MSCW yearbook]
  - Meh Lady, 1934 [MSCW yearbook]
  - Meh Lady, 1935 [MSCW yearbook]
  - Meh Lady, 1936 [MSCW yearbook]
  - The Sampler, 1940 [Sullins College yearbook]
  - Book of Appreciation from Duke University Union, 1984 [book]
  - Audio cassette of Bernstein's "Mass" performance at Duke University, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Audio cassette of Reynolds Price at Duke University, undated
  - Audio cassette of Leontyne Price performance at Duke University, 1975
  - Audio cassette of Lazar Berman performance at Duke University, undated
  - Audio cassette of John Pierre Rampal [i.e., Jean-Pierre Rampal] at Duke University, 1980
  - Audio cassette of Raphael Hillyer at Duke University, 1976
  - Audio cassettes of undetermined origin (50 tapes)
  - Wooden Dagger, undated (Box 10)
  - Letterman Jacket Letters, undated
  - Felt Pennant, undated
  - Nametags, Badges, and Buttons, undated
  - Scraps of Fabric, undated
  - Oversized Photographs, undated
  - Oversized Print Materials, undated
  - The Pohl of Memories, 1967
  - Mounted Promotional Photo of Edith London, undated
  - Ella Fountain Pratt Commemorative Binder, #1 (Box 11)
  - Ella Fountain Pratt Commemorative Binder, #2 (Box 12)
  - Autographed Photograph of Bella Davidovich (Box 13)
  - Autographed Photograph of Itzhak Perlman
  - Autographed Photograph of Leontyne Price
  - Autographed Photograph of Sam Sander
  - Mounted/Matted Promotional Photographs
  - Performance Poster for "Lost Eden" at Duke Chapel, 1982
  - Performance Poster for "Abelard and Heloise" at North Carolina Opera, 1982
  - Performance Poster for "Raleigh's Dream" at North Carolina British-American Festival, 1984
  - North Carolina Association of Art's Councils Certificate of Outstanding Acheivement, 1984
  - Wooden Sorority Paddle, circa 1935
  - Wooden Block painted with Skull and Crossbones, circa 1935
  - Correspondence, circa late 1920's, 1938-1939 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1967 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1973-2006, undated (Box 14)
  - World War II History of Lanier W. Pratt, 1949 Oct. 12 (Box 14)
  - Personal History of Lanier W. Pratt, 1949 Sept. 6 (Box 14)
  - Duke University - Payroll Deduction for Purchase of Series E Defense Savings Bond, 1942 (Box 14)
  - Lanier W. Pratt: Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Lanier W. Pratt: Thesis Materials, 1936-1940 (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - Day Planner, 1997-1998 (Box 14)
  - Music Study Club, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 14)
  - Genealogy: Pratt, Hicks, Lanier, Keesler Families (includes correspondence) (2 folders) (see also Box 17) (Box 14)
  - Letters of Condolence: Ella Fountain Pratt, 2008 (Box 14)
  - Letters of Condolence: Rev. Charles H. Pratt, 1950 Jan.-Feb. (Box 14)
  - Memorial: Rev. Charles H. Pratt, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Wedding Gift Book: Ella and Lanier Pratt, 1936 (Box 14)
  - Duke Artists Series Program and Thank You Note (signed by Leontyne Price), 1974, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Met Centennial Program (signed by Michael Best), 1983 (Box 14)
  - Poems (written by Elizabeth Pratt Hayer), undated (Box 14)
  - Programs for Performances (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Postcards (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1929 (Lanier Pratt, incomplete) (Box 14)
  - Photographs, undated (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1959, undated (Box 14)
  - Photographs, circa 1850-1959 (Box 14)
  - Photographs, circa 1920's-1959 (Box 14)
  - Photographs, circa 1920-1960 (Box 14)
  - Photographs, circa 1940-1965 (Box 14)
  - Photographs, circa 1950's (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1978, 1986, 1988, undated (Box 14)
  - Photographs, 1986, 1997, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Photographs, 1988 (Box 15)
  - Photographs, 1994, undated (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Photographs, 1999, undated (Box 15)
  - Photograph Album, 1966, undated (Box 15)
  - Photographic Negatives: Duke Student Art Show, [circa early 1960's?] (Box 15)
  - Photographic Negatives: Ella and Lanier Pratt in Boston, [1943?] (Box 15)
  - Photographic Negatives, undated (Box 15)
  - Photographic Negatives, undated (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Clippings, 1943-2008, undated (see also Box 17) (Box 16)
  - A.R.C. Life-Saving Service Patch (Box 16)
  - Third Place Medal for 120 yard High Hurdles, 1933 and Third Place Ribbon for Pole Vault (Field Day), 1935 (Mt. Berry School for Boys) (Box 16)
  - Two Charms: Duke University [probably related to the Student Union], one has initials JAV on the back, undated (Box 16)
  - Photographs, undated (oversize) (Box 17)
  - Print of Duke Chapel in the Snow, 1986 (reproduction of original by Alan Cheek) (oversize) (Box 17)
  - Condolence Book, 2008 (presented by the Durham Arts Council)(oversize) (Box 17)
  - Clippings about Sidney Lanier, undated (oversize) (Box 17)
  - Audio-Visual Materials: Master Copies *Use Copy Must Be Made For Patron Use* (Box 18)
    - Lanier Ward Pratt Scrapbook of Mt. Hermon School, Massachusetts, 1926-1929 (DVD-R) (Disc will not read)
    - Ella Fountain Pratt Reception, 2008 Aug. 09 (CD-R) (Disc will not read)
    - "A Service of Witness to the Resurrection and Thanksgiving for the Life of Ella Fountain Kessler Pratt," First Presbyterian Church (Durham, NC), 2008 Aug. 09 (CD)
    - Oral History of Ella Fountain Kessler Pratt by Alicia J. Rouverol
      - 1999 Aug. 19: 2 CD's, 2 Audio-cassettes
      - 1999 Sept. 7: 2 CD's, 2 Audio-cassettes
      - 1999 Sept. 14: 2 CD's, 1 Audio-cassette
      - 1999 Sept. 17: 4 CD's, 2 Audio-cassettes
      - Undated: 2 CD's, 1 Audio-cassette
      - 1993 July 27: 1 CD, 1 Audio-cassette
    - Oral History of Ella Fountain Keesler Pratt by Iris Tillman Hill, 1992 Dec. (2 CD's, 1 Audio-cassette)
    - "Ella Fountain Pratt: Defying Gravity," produced by the Durham Arts Council, copyright 2010 (DVD-R)
    - Scanned Images of Ella Fountain Keesler Pratt (14 CD-R)
    - Scanned Images of Lanier W. Pratt (4 CD-R)
    - Scanned Images of Sam and Lanny Pratt (1 CD-R)
  - Use Copies of Scanned Images and Audio-Visual Materials
    - Scanned Images from Nitrate Negatives (Dvd Discs 1-5)
    - Oral History of Ella Fountain Keesler Pratt by Alicia J. Rouverol
      - 1999 Aug. 19 (Cd Discs 1-2)
      - 1999 Sept. 7 (Cd Discs 1-2)
      - 1999 Sept. 14 (Cd Discs 1-2)
      - 1999 Sept. 17 (Cd Discs 1-4)
- Materials in Conservation, undated, (1 box)
  Several oversized paper items--including a decorative poster-sized map of Greenwood, MS--are currently being treated by Conservation. These items will be made available once treatment is completed.